Guide to the Freedom Socialist Party and Radical Women Newspaper and Pamphlet Collection TAM.653
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Freedom Socialist Party and Radical Women Newspaper and Pamphlet Collection
1937-2002
1973-1982
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Freedom Socialist Party (U.S.)
Radical Women
Gilbert, Helen
TAM.653
12.25 Linear Feet in 12 record cartons and 1 manuscript box
The Freedom Socialist Party and Radical Women were founded in the mid-1960s in Seattle as revolutionary feminist organizations within the socialist movement. The two organizations formally affiliated in 1973. This collection consists of serials and pamphlets collected by the Freedom Socialist Party and Radical Women. The subjects represented in the titles and content of the publications are socialism, feminism, lesbian and gay liberation, indigenous organizing, and prisoners' issues, among others. There are a limited number of international titles. The collection is an excellent source of information about the small presses of the revolutionary Left, as well as the history of the movements reflected in, and publishing, the newspapers and pamphlets.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Helen Gilbert on behalf of Radical Women and the Freedom Socialist Party in 2014. The accession number associated with this gift is 2014.138.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into three series. The first two series are arranged in alphabetical order by title; Series III is arranged in alphabetical order by subject.
Historical/Biographical Note
The Freedom Socialist Party (FSP) was founded in Seattle, Washington in 1966 after a split in the U.S. Socialist Workers Party. Radical Women was created the following year by FSP founder Clara Fraser, her friend Gloria Martin, and activists from Students for a Democratic Society. Both organizations were established in the political contexts of international liberation struggles, the civil rights movement, and the Vietnam War. The political programs of these organizations, heavily influenced by Trotskyism, attempt to situate racial justice, women's, and gay liberation movements within the Marxist framework. Therefore, the FSP and Radical Women look to these historically oppressed groups to provide revolutionary leadership. Radical Women provides trainings for women to assume leadership roles in social justice movements. Both organizations have been active in the anti-Vietnam war movement, union organizing, indigenous struggles and LGBTQ issues. The FSP and Radical Women formally affiliated in 1973.
Scope and Content Note
The collection consists of newspapers and pamphlets collected by the Freedom Socialist Party and Radical Women. The publications span the 1930s to the 2000s, with the bulk from the 1970s to the early 1980s. The collection includes over 300 titles, from primarily American publishers, with a small number of international titles. The serials often only include one or two issues from each title. This collection is particularly strong in the following subject areas: socialism, feminism, gay liberation, civil rights, indigenous organizing and prisoners' issues. A small number of pamphlets address similar topics, with an additional focus on international issues, including Angola, Ireland and South Africa. The collection also includes subject files, which are comprised of newspapers and pamphlets that were arranged topically by the Freedom Socialist Party and Radical Women. The collection is an excellent source of information about the small presses of the revolutionary Left, as well as the history of the movements reflected in, and publishing, the newspapers and pamphlets.
Separated Materials
Duplicate issues were removed from the collection.
Palestine.; Underground newspapers -- United States; Prisoners -- Civil rights -- United States -- Newspapers.; Radicalism -- United States -- Newspapers.; Gay liberation movement -- United States -- Newspapers.; Labor |z United States |v Newspapers.; Prisoners and prisons.; Indians of North America -- Civil rights -- Newspapers.; Civil rights -- United States.; Indigenous peoples |z America.; Women's rights.; Ireland.; Housing -- United States.; Apartheid -- South Africa.; College student newspapers and periodicals.; Landlord and tenant |z United States; Labor journalism -- United States.; Black power.; South Africa; Marxism -- United States.; Feminism |z United States |v Periodicals.; Feminism -- United States -- Newspapers.; Boston (Mass.); Gay rights -- United States.; Lesbians -- United States; New York (N.Y.).; Socialism -- United States.; Seattle (Wash.); Women prisoners |z United States.; Trotskyism -- United States.; Socialist feminism |z United States.; Fourth International; International Socialists (U.S.); Socialist Labor Party; Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America; Spartacist League of the U.S.; Liberation Support Movement. Information Center; Communist Party of the United States of America; Industrial Workers of the World; Gray Panthers; Black Panther Party; National Lawyers Guild; National Organization for Women; Students for a Democratic Society (U.S.); Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee (U.S.); Mobilization for Survival (Organization); Gilbert, Helen
- Series I: Serials by Title, 1937-2002
  Scope and Content Note
  This series represents the bulk of the collection, and includes over 300 different titles published by a large array of organizations. Many titles only include one or two issues, while a few have more complete runs. Titles with a significant number of issues include The Militant (Militant Publishing Company, Socialist Workers Party), The Movement (Student Non-Violent Coordinating Committee and Students for a Democratic Society), The Newsletter (Socialist Labor League), Seattle Gay News (Gay Community Center), and Sojourner (Sojourner Feminist Institute). Publishers with multiple titles include the International Defence and Aid Fund for Southern Africa, the National Lawyers Guild, the United Secretariat of the Fourth International, the National Organization for Women, a variety of Leonard Peltier support groups, and others. Publishers are based both in the U.S. and internationally, and the cities of Seattle, New York, and Boston are particularly well represented. Major subjects in this series include socialism, Trotskyism and Marxism, civil rights, the early feminist and lesbian movements, gay liberation, indigenous organizing, and prisoners' issues.
  - 4 Spartacus Canada Publisher: Spartacus Canada Publishing City of publication: Toronto, ON, 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 30 Day Notice Publisher: Seattle Tenants Union City of publication: Seattle, WA, 1980-1982 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - The Advance Publisher: Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers of America, AFL-CIO City of publication: New York, NY, 1965, 1973, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Africa Latin America Asia Revolution Publisher: Nouvelles Editions Internationales City of publication: Paris, France, 1963-1964 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - African Agenda Publisher: African Agenda City of publication: Chicago, IL, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Akwesasne Notes Publisher: Program in American Studies of the State University of New York at Buffalo, D-Q University, and the Mohawk Nation City of publication: Rooseveltown, NY, 1975-1980 (Box 1, Folder 6-7)
  - Ang Katipunan Publisher: Union of Democratic Filipinos City of publication: Oakland, CA, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - The Bay Area Worker, El Obrero del area de la Bahia City of publication: San Francisco, CA, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - The Black Panther Intercommunal News Service Publisher: Black Panther Party City of publication: Oakland, CA, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Black Politics Publisher: Black Politics City of publication: Berkeley, CA, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Black Scholar Publisher: The Black World Foundation City of publication: Sausalito, CA, 1976-1978 (Box 1, Folder 12-13)
  - Blind Justice Publisher: National Lawyers Guild, N.Y.C. Chapter City of publication: New York, NY, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Briefing Paper on Southern Africa Publisher: International Defence and Aid Fund for Southern Africa City of publication: Cambridge, MA, 1981-1983 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Bulletin in Defense of Marxism Publisher: Fourth International Tendency City of publication: New York, NY, 1985-1989 (Box 1, Folder 16-18)
  - The Burning Spear Publisher: African People's Socialist Party City of publication: Gainesville, FL, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - The Call Publisher: October League City of publication: Chicago, IL, 1976-1977 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - The Campaigner Publisher: National Caucus of Labor Committees City of publication: New York, NY, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - The Catholic Worker Publisher: Catholic Worker Movement City of publication: New York, NY, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Center for Womens Studies and Services Newsletter Publisher: San Diego State University City of publication: San Diego, CA, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Changes Socialist Monthly Publisher: Changes Socialist Monthly City of publication: Detroit, MI, 1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Civil Liberties Publisher: American Civil Liberties Union City of publication: New York, NY, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Class Struggle Publisher: Class Struggle League City of publication: Wollaston, MA, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Class Struggle Publisher: The October League City of publication: Bell Garderns, CA, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Class War Publisher: Class War, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Columbus Free Press City of publication: Columbus, OH, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Come Out Fighting Publisher: Lavender and Red Union City of publication: Los Angeles, CA, 1976-1977 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Common Ground Publisher: Alaska Common Ground Collective City of publication: Anchorage, Juneau and Fairbanks, AK, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Common Sense Publisher: Northern California Alliance City of publication: San Francisco, CA, 1976-77 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Il Comunista Publisher: Il Comunista, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Consumer Outlook Publisher: Seattle Consumer Action Network City of publication: Seattle, WA, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - The Cooper Point Journal Publisher: Evergreen State College City of publication: Olympia, WA, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Coyote Howls Publisher: COYOTE: A Loose Woman's Organization City of publication: San Francisco, CA, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Crazy Horse Spirit Publisher: Leonard Peltier Support Group City of publication: Rapid City, SD, 1982; undated (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - The Daily Publisher: Board of Student Publications of the University of Washington City of publication: Seattle, WA, 1980-1982 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Daily World Publisher: Long View Publishing Co., Inc City of publication: New York, NY, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Dollars and Sense Publisher: Economic Affairs Bureau, Inc City of publication: Somerville, MA, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - dsuq' wub' siatsub (The Suquamish News) City of publication: Suquamish, WA, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Eagle Wing Press Publisher: Eagle Wing Press, Inc City of publication: Naugatuck, CT, 1982-1983 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Education Publisher: Central Area Motivation Program City of publication: Seattle, WA, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Elder Affairs Publisher: Seattle-King County Division on Aging City of publication: Seattle, WA, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Feminist Review Publisher: Feminist Review City of publication: London, UK, 1980-1982, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 7-8)
  - Focus on Political Repression in South Africa Publisher: International Defence and Aid Fund for Southern Africa City of publication: Cambridge, MA, 1979-1983 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Forward Publisher: Forward Publishing Association City of publication: Toronto, ON, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - The Fourth International Publisher: Executive Committee of the Fourth International City of publication: Detroit, MI, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Fremont Forum Publisher: Fremont Public Association City of publication: Seattle, WA, 1980-1982 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Friends of the Filipino People Bulletin Publisher: Friends of the Filipino People City of publication: Washington, D.C., 1978-1980 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Gay Community Center (GCC) Newsletter Publisher: Community Multi-Service Center City of publication: Seattle, WA, 1980-1981 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Gay Community News Publisher: Gay Community News City of publication: Boston, MA, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 15-16)
  - Gay Left Publisher: Gay Left City of publication: London, UK, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Gay Star Publisher: Northern Ireland Gay Rights Association City of publication: Belfast, Northern Ireland, undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Gay Tide Publisher: Vancouver Gay Alliance Towards Equality City of publication: Vancouver, BC, 1974-1978 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Gender and Society Publisher: Sociologists for Women in Society City of publication: Newburry Park, CA, 1987-1988 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Grass Roots Publisher: Grass Roots City of publication: Washington, D.C., 1976 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Gray Panther Network Publisher: Gray Panther Network City of publication: Philadelphia, PA, 1979-1982 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Gray Panther Project Fund Publisher: Gray Panther Network City of publication: Philadelphia, PA, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - El Grito del Norte Publisher: El Grito del Norte City of publication: Las Vegas, NM, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - La Guardia City of publication: New York, NY, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Guardian Publisher: Guardian City of publication: New York, NY, 1977; 1982 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Guild Notes Publisher: National Lawyers Guild City of publication: New York, NY, 1976-1977 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - The Gwarth-EE-Lass Report Publisher: Leonard Peltier Support Group City of publication: Mohegan Lake, NY, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Hapotoc News Publisher: Hapotoc News City of publication: Amsterdam, Holland, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - I.D.A.F News Notes Publisher: United States Committee for the International Defense and Aid Fund for Southern Africa City of publication: Cambridge, MA, 1982-1983 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - In These Times Publisher: In These Times City of publication: Chicago, IL, 1981-1982 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Indian Valley Echo Publisher: Indian Valley Colleges City of publication: Novato, CA, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Indian Voice Publisher: Small Tribes Organization of Western Washington City of publication: Sumner, WA, 1979-1981 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Indigena Publisher: Indigena City of publication: Berkeley, CA, 1975-1976 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Industrial Worker Publisher: Industrial Workers of the World City of publication: Chicago, IL, 1976-1982 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Inprecor Publisher: United Secretariat of the Fourth International City of publication: Argenteuil, France, 1975-1977 (Box 3, Folder 6-7)
  - Intercontinental Press Publisher: Intercontinental Press City of publication: New York, NY, 1979, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Internal Information Bulletin Publisher: Socialist Workers Party City of publication: New York, NY, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - International Publisher: International Marxist Group City of publication: London, UK, 1979-1982 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - International Publisher: International Marxist Group - British Section of the Fourth International City of publication: London, UK, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - The International Publisher: Peoples Socialist International City of publication: San Francisco, CA, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - International Correspondence Publisher: International Correspondence, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - International Examiner Publisher: Journal of Seattle's Asian Communities City of publication: Seattle, WA, 1976, 1980-1983 (Box 3, Folder 14-16)
  - International Internal Discussion Bulletin Publisher: United Secretariat of the Fourth International City of publication: New York, NY, 1973, 1976-1977 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - International Review Publisher: International Communist Current City of publication: London, UK, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - International Socialist Review Publisher: International Socialist Review Publishing Association City of publication: New York, NY, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - International Viewpoint Publisher: United Secretariat of the Fourth International City of publication: Montreuil, France, 1983-1987 (Box 3, Folder 20-22)
  - Iran Liberation Publisher: Union of Moslem Iranian Students Societies Outside Iran, supporters of the People's Mojahedin Organization of Iran City of publication: New York, NY, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Jewish Currents Publisher: Jewish Currents City of publication: New York, NY, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - The Journal of Intergroup Relations Publisher: National Association of Human Rights Workers City of publication: Louisville, KY, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Justice Publisher: International Ladies Garment Workers Union City of publication: New York, NY, 1981-1982 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Labor News Publisher: Socialist League City of publication: San Francisco, CA, 1980-1981 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Labor Newsletter Publisher: National Lawyers Guild City of publication: San Jose, CA, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Labor Notes Publisher: Labor Education and Research Project City of publication: Detroit, MI, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Labor Today Publisher: Trade Union Action and Democracy City of publication: Chicago, IL, 1981-1982 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Labor Unity Publisher: Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers City of publication: New York, NY, 1977-1982 (Box 4, Folder 8-9)
  - Labor World Publisher: Spokane, Washington Labor Council AFL-CIO and the Spokane Building and Construction Trades Council City of publication: Spokane, WA, 1978, 1980-1982 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Labour Action Publisher: Labour Action Committee City of publication: Toronto, ON, 1972-1973 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Latin America and Empire Report Publisher: North American Congress on Latin America, Inc. City of publication: New York, NY, 1973-1974 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Lesbian Flash City of publication: Seattle, WA, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - The Letter Publisher: Institute for Contemporary Studies City of publication: San Francisco, CA, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Letter from China Publisher: Anna Louise Strong City of publication: Peking, China, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Light Brigade Publisher: Light Brigade City of publication: Seattle, WA, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Lights with Current Publisher: Media Lights, Inc. City of publication: Seattle, WA, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Magnus: A Journal of Collective Faggotry Publisher: Magnus Collective City of publication: San Francisco, CA, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - El Malcriado Publisher: United Farm Workers, AFL-CIO City of publication: Keene, CA, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Marxist Bulletin Publisher: Sparticist City of publication: New York, NY, 1963-1971 (Box 4, Folder 20-24)
  - MEJANE Publisher: MEJANE City of publication: Sydney, Australia, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Middle East Report Publisher: Middle East Research and Information Project City of publication: Washington D.C., 1987-1988 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - The Militant Publisher: The Militant (Socialist Workers Party) City of publication: New York, NY, 1971-1982 (Box 4, Folder 27-28, Box 5, Folder 1-5)
  - The Militant Publisher: Militant Publishing Company City of publication: Toronto, ON, 1977 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - The Mobilizer Publisher: Mobilization for Survival City of publication: New York, NY, 1982 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Monthly Review Publisher: Monthly Review Foundation, Inc. City of publication: New York, NY, 1982 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Morning Due: Journal of Men Against Sexism Publisher: Morning Due City of publication: Seattle, WA, 1975-1977 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Mother Jones Publisher: Foundation for National Progress City of publication: Manchester, UK, 1979 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Moving On Publisher: New American Movement City of publication: Chicago, IL, 1977 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - The Movement Publisher: The Movement Press, Student Non-Violent Coordinating Committee and Students for a Democratic Society City of publication: San Francisco, CA, 1968-1970 (Box 5, Folder 12-13)
  - MPOC Bulletin Publisher: Mass Party Organizing Committee City of publication: New York, NY, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - The Nation Publisher: Nation Enterprises City of publication: New York, NY, 1980-1981 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - NESIKA Publisher: British Columbia Association of Non Status Indians City of publication: Vancouver, BC, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - New American Movement Publisher: New American Movement City of publication: Oakland, CA, 1975-1976 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - New Indicator Publisher: New Indicator Collective, University of California at San Diego City of publication: La Jolla, CA, 1982 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - The New Republic Publisher: The New Republic City of publication: Washington D.C., 1963 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - The New Socialist City of publication: Denver, CO, 1980, 1982 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - New Times Publisher: Trud (Moscow) City of publication: New York, NY, 1964 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - New Women's Times Feminist Review Publisher: New Women's Times City of publication: Rochester, NY, 1981 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - New World Communications City of publication: Cambridge, MA, 1974 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - New World Review Publisher: N.W.R. Publications, Inc. City of publication: New York, NY, 1974 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - The New York Alliance Publisher: Labor Community Alliance for Change City of publication: New York, NY, 1979-1981 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - News and Letters Publisher: News and Letters City of publication: Detroit, MI, 1979-1982 (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - News Gay Community Center Publisher: Gay Community Center City of publication: Seattle, WA, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - The Newsletter Publisher: Socialist Labour League City of publication: London, UK, 1957-1958, 1964-1968 (Box 6, Folder 1-3, Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Newsletter ClearingHouse Publisher: People's Coalition for Peace and Justice City of publication: Seattle, WA, 1975 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - No More Fun and Games Publisher: Female Liberation City of publication: Somerville, MA, 1969 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Northern Sun News Publisher: Northern Sun Alliance City of publication: Minneapolis, MN, 1981 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Northwest Access Publisher: Third World People in Communications City of publication: Seattle, WA, 1976 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Northwest Indian News Publisher: Indians Into Communications Association, Inc. City of publication: Seattle, WA, 1976-1977 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Northwest Passage Publisher: Northwest Passage, Inc. City of publication: Bellingham, WA, 1969-1981 (Box 6, Folder 9-12)
  - Northwest Women's Studies Resource Bank Newsletter Publisher: Northwest Women's Studies Resource Bank Newsletter City of publication: Pullman, WA, 1977-1982 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - NOW Times Enumclaw Newsletter Publisher: National Organization for Women, undated (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Nowsletter Publisher: National Organization for Women City of publication: Seattle, WA, 1978 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Nucleaus Publisher: Union of Concerned Scientists City of publication: Cambridge, MA, 1981 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Old Mole Publisher: Revolutionary Marxist Group City of publication: Toronto, ON, 1975 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - On Parade! Publisher: Lesbian/Gay Freedom Day Committee City of publication: San Francisco, CA, 1981 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Open Road Publisher: The Open Road City of publication: Vancouver, BC, 1976-1977 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Organizing Notes Publisher: Campaign for Political Rights City of publication: Washington, D.C, 1977-1981 (Box 6, Folder 20-21)